and it's high noon in Old Cheyenne.
Welcome to the September 22nd meeting of
the finance committee. Call the meeting
to order. Uh, if you have a cell phone,
please make sure it's on
silent or vibrate when making public
comment. Clearly identify yourself. If
you're using online, raise use the
raised hand function.
Uh, approach the podium and turn the
microphone on. Identify yourself and at
the end of this uh agenda, there will be
no additional business discussed. And
more most importantly, all communication
goes through the chair clerk. First item
>> number 19 resolution supporting the
continuation of the optional 1% sales
tax for calendar years 2027 through 2030
and pledging that all revenues derived
from this tax will be used for project
described in this resolution.
>> Staff report
>> Vicky Niche public works. Um there is a
substitute for this. I believe that uh
Jennifer has provided that to you. There
are two minor changes in that
substitute. Um it will it's on page
those two changes are on page four and
I'll thank Mr. Wolf for pointing out my
errors. Thank you Mr. Wolf so that we
could get this exactly right. Um under
human services agencies uh the p the
amount of money is correct but the
percentage was incorrect. Instead of
2.00% 00% it should be 1.25%.
And um just below that Cheyen Larmy
County Economic Development again the
amount the $800,000 is correct but the
percentage should be 1.00%
uh instead of the 1.60%.
>> Okay.
So with that I will move through the
1% resolution. We are the city has
required ourselves by ordinance to um
tell the voters how we intend to use the
tax. So the fifth penny sales tax is uh
a four-year tax that is collected over
the fouryear period starting the 1 of
January. It would be for this year uh
this coming year 2027 through uh year
2020 2030
and
that is uh and that is a 4-year tax. We
are estimating a collection of $80
million. We estimate the number so that
we can budget uh annually to uh let
people know how much we intend to spend.
So, this resolution explains how we
intend to spend the $80 million that we
are estimating to collect over the four
years. So, I'll just do a um kind of a
comparison with the last tax so that
everybody knows where we're at and what
the changes the differences are. Um, if
you go to page two, the street and road
maintenance and construction portion of
the tax, that is um 80% of the tax or
$64 million out of the 80 million. And
that is why most people refer to this as
the road tax. It's been that since 1978
when it first was uh implemented. So, of
that $64 million,
um, we are putting 40 million in
contract maintenance, 8 million in
street and alley maintenance, 4 million
in traffic maintenance, 4 million in
construction and administration, and 8
million in drainage. Um, comparatively,
contract maintenance was uh in the last
tax 20 million. So, we've doubled that
number, and I'll explain how we got
there. Um the street and alley was 5
million, it is now 8 million. In the
last tax, the traffic uh maintenance was
3 million. We've moved that up to 4
million. Uh administration management,
which is basically the construction
uh management office and along with the
administrative costs of the tax uh is
what that pays for. It this does not pay
for all of that. The rest is covered
first with interest. any interest that
we receive and that's explained later in
the in the resolution as well as any
overage.
And then the drainage uh is $8 million
compared to 4 million the last time. So
we've significantly increased that,
doubled it. In fact, there was a sixth
portion um as you'll see the numbers
along the side one through five are what
we're funding. Um there was a si a
number six which was projects. Instead
of specifying a pro specific projects,
we've decided to just move all of that
all of those funds into contract
maintenance which uh and then change the
wording a little bit to include that we
could do overlays uh chip slurry micro
uh micro crack seals, those kinds of
things, traffic signals, concrete work.
And then we could do construction,
reconstruction, and renovation, which
would be improvements on the roads. So
all of there's a little bit of wording
change in there to allow that. So now
any project would also come from that
contract maintenance line item.
On the next page, which would be the
third page of the of the uh resolution
is other projects and agencies. So the
remaining uh from the s we took eight
started with 80 million we took 64
million out for the roads and we have 16
million remaining. So this is the
portion that starts telling you how we
plan to use that money. So that 20% or
$16 million starts with fire rescue.
They have the same percentage as the
last tax 4% um but their number goes
from 2 million to 3.2 million.
The police department again has the same
percentage 5%
but they go from 2.5 million to 4
million.
Community recreation and events uh they
did have their actual percentage went up
along with the amount of money they're
going to receive. Uh in the last tax
that was 2.375
million. In this tax it will be 4
million according to this proposal. and
their uh percentage went up from 4.75 to
5%. And this is for uh rightway
maintenance basically.
Then we've added a new um section which
is community wreck and events parking
lot maintenance. So that is where the
parking lot maintenance money will be in
the new tax. Um $1.4 million. That uh
percentage is 0175.
Next is the compliance department. They
did they were in the last tax. They
received $250,000
um in this coming tax. They will go up
to 400,000.
And they're I believe that uh percentage
remains the same. And then a new one uh
another one new which is public works
department facilities maintenance. Um,
this is uh $400,000 and for the
four-year period and it is new again at
050%.
The next piece is capital equipment.
This one did go down. The percentage
before was not quite 1%, it was 9854%.
Um, and we have decreased that to.5.
It was $492,74
last the last four-year tax. it is
400,000. Now these uh the things that we
buy with these, we bought uh multiple
compliance vehicles. We pay for the
emergency notification software which is
called alert media. Um we've bought
furniture. We recently bought some
furniture for HR human resources. Bought
some camera equipment for the new uh PIO
uh assistant Ben Silver. Those are the
kinds of things that we normally uh use
that for. And those funds are used at
the mayor's discretion.
On the next page, the fourth page,
we have city county health department
that uh actually went their percentage
went down slightly from 67
down to 050%.
They received in the last tax $335,000
but their amount because of the
increased estimate will go up to
$400,000.
Um human services agencies again their
uh percentage went down from 2% to
1.25%.
Um it is $1 million which is exactly the
same as it was in the last tax. And then
the last portion there is the Cheyenne
Larmy County Economic Development that
was uh the percentage is down from 1.60%
to 1% and but the uh amount remains the
same $800,000
um in the last tax, $800,000 in this
tax. Um that also has some wording
changes in the economic development
portion. um instead of going to the uh
Joint Powers Economic Development Board,
these funds will be available to the
city council for dispersement instead.
Um and then the last is really uh
that explains that we're going to
estimate 80 $80 million which is 100% of
what we're estimating and then uh talks
about that interest that I mentioned
earlier will go first to pay the
administrative administration and
management costs of the tax and um it
also pays costs uh of the United Way
administering the human services agency
funding which is uh and has been for
quite some time $12,500
each year.
Um and then it goes on to talk about in
the last be it further resolved um on
the bottom of page four that any excess
of the estimated uh in excess of 8 the
$80 million will be called overage funds
and talks about how those funds will be
dispersed. And um the
first is used to again after interest to
pay for the administrative and
management costs of the 1% tax and
administering that tax. The remaining
overage funds um go to if you look at
the next page there are three paragraphs
there that describe how they'll go.
Again streeten road maintenance and
drainage 80% again that's why we call it
the road tax. So any overage 80% goes
directly to street and road maintenance.
Um number two, public works department
uh 10% goes to towards facilities
maintenance. Those kind uh those things
are will help pay for things that we
need at um some of our bigger and more
expensive facilities like the depot, the
civic center, the beast, the municipal
building as it sits and the parking
garages, those kinds of things. um
covers everything if you can imagine
your house times a million square foot
[laughter] what it costs to to maintain
those. So um so we've so that is the
same percentage that was in the last
tax.
Um and then other projects and agencies
uh the remaining 10% so 80% to streets
and roads 10% to facilities. The
remaining 10% would be broken out to
fire and rescue, police, community wreck
and events, community wreck and events
just the parking lots and then the
compliance department. Um the some of
the entities that receive 1% sales tax
do not receive overage. So that would be
the capital equipment or the the mayor's
discretionary funds. Um that does not
receive overage. City county health does
not receive overage. Human services does
not receive overage and the economic
development line will not receive
overage. Um and then just the be it
finally resolved if we do not collect
the 80 million that would be a bad thing
but we'll have to come back to the
council and uh reallocate those funds
with a new resolution. We have done that
once in the past. Um it was tough to do
but hopefully our revenues are showing
that um and I have those numbers. I
think
for overage in uh
2015 to 2018 we collected 13 almost $14
million. In 2019 to 2022, we collected
uh 31
uh 31,600,000
about and then in 23 to 26, we have
collected so far 30,300,000
in overage. So just that's why we're
moving that uh number up to 80 million
because we believe that is a very a very
reasonable number um to estimate. So
with that, I have be happy to answer any
questions.
>> Any comments from or questions from the
committee for director Council White?
>> Mr. Chair, through you. Uh Vicki, just
for the record, um so folks know this is
to go on the November ballot. Is that
correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Thank you.
>> Nothing else from the committee for the
director. We'll go to public comment in
the room. Any public comment in the room
on this item?
Seeing none, we'll go to public comment
online.
Any public comment online on this item?
Seeing none, come back to the committee.
>> Mr. Chair, I move to adopt. Second move
by Council White, seconded by Councilman
Moody.
>> Mr. Chair, I move to amend by substitute
dated September 22nd, 2026.
>> Second.
>> Okay. Substitute moved by Councilman
White, second by Council Moody. Any
further discussion?
All those in favor signify by saying I.
Any opposed?
Back to the main motion.
All in favor signify by saying I. Any
opposed? Seeing that that resolution is
unanimous, the recommendation in the
finance committee at the next meeting of
the governing body will be to adopt.
Next item
>> number 20 resolution reappropriating the
fiscal year 2026 budget of the city of
Cheyenne according to the provisions of
Wyoming state statutes 16-4-112
and 16-4-113.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon, chairman, members of the
finance committee. Uh my name is Robin
Lman. I'm the city treasurer. Thank you
for the opportunity to provide some
additional information on the final
reappropriation for last fiscal year.
The memo I provided contains the full
details, but I want to highlight the key
points, particularly those affecting the
general fund reserves and the self-
insurance fund. The total
reappropriation request is approximately
$5 million. of that amount 1,631,979
is being requested from general fund
reserves. The remaining approximately
3.3 million is supported by additional
revenue and reserves from our other
funds. So those requests do not use
general fund reserves. The majority of
the general fund requests reflects the
way we manage our budget throughout the
year.
As I have explained in the past, there
are certain costs that are very
difficult or impossible to accurately
predict when we predict prepare the
budget more than a year in advance.
These include employee sick and vacation
vac payouts for when an employee leaves
the city, accident related costs,
vandalism and theft, utilities, fleet
fuel, parts and labor. Rather than
overbudgeting these items in every
department and tying up funds that may
not be needed, we budget them based on
the best information available and make
necessary adjustments at year end. We
also do not require departments to
reduce their other operating
expenditures to cover costs that they
really have very little control over.
For fiscal year 2026, we are requesting
approximately 97,000 for accident and
damage claims,
120,000 for natural gas and electricity
increases, 142,000 for fleet cost
increases,
172,000 for employee sick and vacation
payouts, and approximately 36,000 for
vandalism and theft expenses.
There are also several larger, more
specific general fund requests that I
want to point out. We are requesting
149,000 for higher than anticipated
inmate housing costs at the Larmy County
Detention Center as well as an
approximately 378,000 for the combined
communication center. The communication
center increase was primarily due to
several previously hard to fill vacate
vacant positions being filled during the
year.
We are also requesting approximately
155,000 for the municipal court and
former senior center renovation design
contract that was previously approved by
the governing body and $350,000 for the
purchase of the property at 803 West
16th Street which was previously
approved by the governing body as well.
I also want to provide some context on
the self- insurance fund request because
the $2.7 million reappropriation is a
very large number. Since the city is
self-insured, we essentially act as our
own health insurance company. The
premiums paid by the city and our
employees go into this fund and we use
those dollars to pay our employees
health care claim expenses.
Fiscal year 2026 was a particularly high
claims year. Our benefit consultant has
advised us that based on their
experience, the self insurance, their
self-funded plan can generally expect a
more difficult claims year every five
years.
We've had our plan for four years now
and we've had very good claims
experience in fiscal years 23, 24, and
25.
We also purchase stop-loss insurance to
protect the city when claims become
exceptionally high. It protects us both
when an individual has extremely high
medical expenses and when the city's
claims as a whole becomes exceptionally
high. For the overall plan, the
insurance begins paying when our claims
reach 100% of an the established
threshold.
At the end of fiscal year 26, we were
still below that threshold at 87%.
The goal is 80% or lower, which is based
on the Affordable Care Act's requirement
that 80% of all premiums collected must
go to pay for medical care and quality
improvement rather than administration,
overhead, and profit. It is also
important to understand that the 2.7
million reappropriation does not
represent a $2.7 million loss to the
fund. We received approximately 12.2 2
million in revenue during the year and
had 12.9 million in expenses. So the
self- insurance fund decreased
approximately by 690,000 for the entire
fiscal year. The fund ended June 30th
with a reserve of approximately $3.7
million.
For context, when we began the self-
insurance fund on July 1st of 2022, we
started with approximately 1.4 million
in reserves. As far as how much we
should maintain in reserves, our
benefits consultant has recommended a
minimum of six months of claim expenses
with 12 months being the ideal target.
Looking at our claims experience over
the four years we have been
self-insured, we have averaged
approximately 9.3 million in claims
annually. Based on that average, 6
months would be approximately 4.7
million and 12 months would be
approximately 9.3 million. As I said, we
ended fiscal year 26 with approximately
3.7 million, which represents just under
five months of average claims expenses.
So, our first goal is to maintain at
that least at least at the six-month
level and over time continue toward the
longer term reserve level recommended by
our benefits consultant. This is why we
build reserves in the first place. They
allow us to absorb a higher claims year
like fiscal year 2026 without
immediately having to make significant
changes to employee benefits or
contributions. In fact, that was the
reason for establishing the reserve
target when we first became
self-insured. You may also recall
through the fiscal year 27 budget
process, the governing body approved a
$1 million transfer from general fund
reserves to the self- insurance fund.
That $1 million is not included in the
$3.7 million balance that I just
provided. Once that transfer is
included, we began fiscal year 27 with
the approximately 4.7 million in
reserves, which puts us exactly at our
six-month minimum target reserve level
target based on the four years of
average claims experience. I am happy to
answer any questions you may have on
these requests and I believe most of the
applicable directors are in the room if
you have questions on other items. Thank
you. Okay. Comments or questions from
the committee for the treasure
council.
>> Yeah. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Three. Uh,
this will probably be more for director
Sanchez uh for on page two with the uh
golf course uh accidents. Is that from
now until is that from January until
now?
>> Mr. Chair, through you I I could not
hear you could hear that question.
>> I apologize. Uh, thank you Mr. Turn
through. Thank you, Mr. Sanchez, my
apologies again. Um, on page two where
it has the golf courses, the claims, did
that start in January until now?
Mr. Chair, for you, this would have
started in July of 25 to through June
30th of 26.
>> Okay, that's all I have for them.
>> Mr. Councilman White
>> to to kind of piggyback on Councilman
Moody's question, and I know it's a
minuscule amount in the grand scheme of
things, but
five different unknown vehicles damaged
the golf course fence over the period of
a year. Is there any way we can
I I don't know. I don't know how you
stop that, but it seems Gosh, that seems
like a lot,
>> Mr. Chair, through you. I'm not sure of
a of a good solution. We're surrounded
by a lot of roads. Um, and some of the
intersections are are a little bit
tight. Um,
>> and I know that staff has put up extra
signage, reflection signs, anything to
kind of draw more attention that you
shouldn't be driving your car into this
area.
>> Doesn't seem to have worked.
>> We're at a point where then it becomes a
distraction.
>> Yeah.
So
yeah, good good question. Um, okay,
Councilman.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. Through you, and
again, it can be for anybody can answer.
For the vandalism and thefts on page
four, I understand some we don't know
the vehicles, any of these. Were we
caught the person? Were they prosecuted
and convicted? And have we tried to
obtain restitution from them?
Oh, director.
>> Mr. Chairman, through you to Councilman
Moody. Um, of course, always when we
have a a situation where there's
property damage involving city- owned
property, um, we will do our best to get
an estimate for repairs, provide that to
the courts. Obviously, it's the court
that makes a determination as to what
the restitution amount would be, if any
restitution. Um, there could be jail
time served in in lie of that. So, it's
really hard to give a a specific answer
or pen an answer to that, but yes, the
simple answer is we always try to
recover any uh claimage that we can
through uh a claim on their vehicle um
or through restitution.
[snorts]
>> Okay, seeing no more questions from the
committee, we'll go to public comment in
the room. Any public comment in the room
on this item?
Seeing none, we'll go to public comment
online. Any public comment online on
this item?
No public comment online. Come back to
the committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to adopt.
>> It's been moved by Councilman White,
second by Councilman Wolf. Any further
comments or questions?
All in favor signify by saying I.
Seeing there's none opposed that that
recommendation is unanimous from the
finance committee to the governing body
at our next meeting. [gasps] Next item
>> number 26F Wyoming rule public transit
program fiscal year 2027 subreient
agreement between the city of Cheyenne
transit program and the Wyoming
department of transportation local
government coordination office. staff
report.
>> Good afternoon, Aaron Johnson, Cheyenne
Transit Program Administrator. Um to the
committee, this is for $32,862
that we use for our local match for our
federal operations for the fiscal year
2027.
>> And I will stand by for comments.
>> Questions for Miss Johnson from the
committee?
Oh, seeing none, we'll go to public
comment in the room. Any public comment
in the room on this item? [sighs]
Any public comment online on this item?
>> No public comment online. Back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve an
amount not to exceed $32,862.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
second by Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
All in favor signify by saying I
see and there any opposed. The
recommendation of the finance committee.
The next meeting of the governing body
will be to accept the bid
>> number 26G agreement between the city of
Cheyenne and Brian Colstrom doing
business as Put Hut for premises
premises used as a miniature golf course
in Lions Park. [snorts]
>> Staffry Park.
>> Mr. Chair Jason Sanchez community wreck
and events. before you and for your
consideration is a lease agreement with
Brian Charlesstrom for the P uh in Lions
Park. Uh this is for a five-year lease.
Uh Mr. Charlestrom has been in Lions
Park for decades. He's been a great
tenant. Um easy to work with. Um he pays
uh the city a fee each year for having
the in Lions Park. Um this just
stretches us out for another five years.
It identifies uh the agreements, the
arrangements that we've had previously.
Um, and I'll stand by for any questions.
And Mr. Charlesstrom is here as well.
>> Any comments or questions from the
committee for the director.
>> Uh, Mr. [clears throat] Chairman, thank
you through you. Um, thank you, Director
Sanchez. Um, I just want to as somebody
who lives right near there and whose
kids went to the P hut and, uh, I'm
delighted it's going to continue in
operation and thank you for the city's
support and thank you, Mr. Charlestrom
for your continued support of it. I
think it's a great uh amenity and
terrific connection to a long history in
the city. So
did any uh other comments or questions
from the committee?
We go to public comment in the room. Any
public comment in the room on this item?
Any public comment online?
No. Come back to the committee. That's
your pleasure.
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to approve.
>> Second.
>> Moved by Council Wolf, second by
Councilman Moody. Any other further
comments or questions?
>> Uh, no. Thank you.
>> Okay. All in favor signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous. The
recommendation of the finance committee,
the next meeting of the governing body
will be to approve. Next item,
>> number 26H. lease agreement between the
city of Cheyenne and the Cheyenne Depot
museum incorporated for the operation
and use of the depot building.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> due to the nature of my wife's position
with the depot, I will have to recuse
myself from this item.
>> Okay, understood.
>> Mr. Chair, Jason Sanchez, community
wreck and events before you and for your
consideration is a new lease with the
depot. And I will uh start by explaining
that the the lease we had was created uh
almost 25 years ago and it made sense at
the time. Some of the vocabulary that
was in the lease. Uh but since then some
things have changed over the course of
20 years. Uh Frontier Days is not they
don't have museum in the building. The
depot museum is run uh independently. Um
some of the the items that the city
maintains and the areas that the depot
maintains were not clearly called out
and we have corrected that in this
agreement. Uh we reduced it from a
25-year lease to a 10-year lease with
two 5-year options and that just gives
future um uh DDA board members and
director as well as the city an
opportunity to revisit and make changes
in a timely manner instead of waiting 25
years to make changes. Um, I've been
working with Christie, uh, the depot,
uh, manager for probably a year now on
this contract and their board. We are
all, uh, after going back and forth,
we're all in agreement of the theou
that's before you. Um, it does call out
the city's responsibilities. We still
maintain, uh, the elevator, the elevator
service contract, fire extinguisher
contract. We still do the exterior
maintenance. U, they are responsible for
the interior maintenance. and and
recently we did a lot of uh upgrades and
improvements. And so they will be
maintaining, you know, normal wear and
tear from their tenants. They will
collect rent from their tenants. They
will uh have the opportunity to sell
beer on the plaza on Fridays on the
plaza, but they will also pay for the
security and the insurance that's
necessary for that service. Uh the
proceeds from the beer sales are applied
directly to the maintenance of the
interior of the building. And the city
will also um we we've been occupying
space in the in the depot and that will
continue. We call that out in this
lease. Um I will stand by for questions
as well as we have three members of the
depot here to help answer questions if I
can.
>> Comments or questions from the committee
for director Sanchez?
Councilman Wolf.
>> Mr. Chairman, thank you through you. Um
thank you Mr. Sanchez and and thank you
to the Christa and the board who have uh
made major improvements in this building
and and you director have have obviously
been instrumental in that and passed on
the the six penny. Um I think there were
plans to uh spend some of the money to
renovate the museum. Is is that am I
correct in that? And what are the plans
for that?
>> Mr. Chair, that is correct. on the last
six penny proposition. Uh there was a
proposition to uh renovate uh the museum
portion of the depot. That's the last
piece that we we haven't touched yet. Um
the first phase, we we landscaped the
southern exterior. We built the cafe on
the first floor. We renovated the
restrooms and we did u some repairs to
the facade. On the second phase, we
painted all of the second and third
floor. We replaced the carpet. We added
some windows to some of the offices. We
repainted the windows on the exterior.
We put the new um uh copper. Uh we redid
the plaza, the concrete, and the the
bricks. Uh put the new shade structure.
So, this is the piece that hasn't been
touched yet, and that's the museum. Uh
with the support of the community, we'll
go um start on the design. Uh we'll uh
include the community in the design and
uh have some meetings and opportunities
for people to comment what they would
like to see. And then we'll build a
trash enclosure. Uh right now all the
dumpsters and all the trash cans just
sit out in the parking lot which I think
detracts from the the beauty of the
building and so those are to come both
projects.
>> Any other comments or questions from the
committee?
Uh Jason I had had one uh I don't know
if you know this but does the restaurant
share Wi-Fi with the rest of the
building? Is that all on one? They
don't.
>> Mr. Chair, it does not appear that they
do.
>> Okay. Well, I've had some complaints
about that Wi-Fi in the restaurant area
just
for their um satellite that they're
running for their televisions, games
that that keeps going off during the
middle of the games and
Okay,
let we'll let them know. Okay, thank
you. Uh we'll go to public comment in
the room. Any
public comment in the room on this item?
Seeing none, public comment online.
Public comment online. None. Back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, I move to approve.
Second.
>> Been moved by Councilman Moody, second
by Councilman Wolf. Any further
discussion?
All in favor signify by saying I.
Seeing that there's none opposed, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting governing body will
be to approve. Next item
>> number 27D. Consideration to purchase
between the city of Cheyenne, LN Curtis,
and Suns Incorporated for the purchase
of 90 sets of firefighting turnout gear
for Cheyenne Fire Rescue.
>> Staff report. Good afternoon, finance
committee and chair. My name is Ryan
Anderson, battalion chief with Shine
Fire Rescue. The proposal for you is for
the purchase of 90 sets of firefighting
turnout gear. Each set includes uh an
ensemble of a coat and pants. The quote
for 90 sets totals $331,49160.
This was a successful proposition within
the last six penny. One thing
[clears throat] I want to bring to your
attention, I'd like you guys to refer to
quotes that were dated 918. And I'll
discuss the substitution later on in
this presentation.
[clears throat]
Uh these sets are manufactured by Globe
MSA. The uh sole supplier of Globe MSA
for this region is LN Curtis. The Soul
Source acquisition has been approved by
purchasing manager TJ Bartlebort and the
Soul Source letter is included in the
documentation provided. Um, Ellen,
Curtis, and Globe have uh committed to a
90 business day delivery time once the
order is placed. Uh, just a little bit
of background for your information. NFPA
19 uh70, the National Fire Protection
Association, uh, certifies structural
turnout gear for 10 years. Once that
10-year um, limit is reached, it can be
utilized for non-live fire training. We
typically rotate that older gear out to
our fire academy and let our recruits
use and abuse it, if you will, dragging
it along the ground, uh, and so forth,
but it can't be used in live fire
situations.
Um, per our CLA with [clears throat] the
city, um, each Shine firefighter is
issued two sets of turnout gear. Second
sets necessary to due to the increased
risks of exposure to carcinogenic agents
that contaminate gear after a structure
fire. The clean set is back at their
stations and can be placed into service
immediately uh upon return. And while
the contaminated set is properly
decontaminated and dried inhouse by our
personnel, this therefore reduces
firefighter downtime and provides them
the proper PPE that they need almost
instantaneously.
So, the turnout gear we're discussing uh
in this purchase will replace an
original set that was u bought in 2016,
and I'll refer to it as the orange trim
sets. Um, the reason we do that, we
[clears throat] alternate between yellow
trim and orange trim so we can best
identify our primary set and our backup
set. So that way a fire officer on scene
can wonder why his firefighter has been
in his backup set for an extended period
of time. Is it out of service due to
repair? Is there something else going
on? Um, the substitution that I
referenced earlier, um, we initially
were pursuing their, um,
mid highlevel brand of globe gear called
Extreme Pro. um and had proceeded
through the sizing process. We actually
just received the um trial sets about a
month ago. Uh unfortunately once we got
them, we found there was a vast
difference in the sizing. I'm already a
big guy and my coat fit me like a circus
tent. Um kind of what we came to the
conclusion was is new isn't always
better. We wanted to go back to what we
know and what we really enjoy and what
we've been told is the best gear guys
have worn online. And so, um, Globe and
Ellen Curtis were gracious enough to
give us a promotional pricing for the G
Extreme 3.0 compared to the Pro. So,
that's what the substitute is is as it
relates to. Um, there's no price change.
It's for the 90 sets. It's literally
just a change in description to make
sure that we're providing our guys with
the gear that they like, that they know,
that we're familiar with. Um, like I
said, new isn't always better. We're
finding through this. So, I appreciate
your uh consideration. I'm happy to
answer any questions.
>> Any comments or questions for
>> um Thank you, Mr. Chairman. Through you,
um are are these uh and thank you for
your presentation, Chief. Um are these
are these sized individuals or they
>> Yes, sir. So, um what we'll do and and
actually that's kind of another
fortunate thing with us going back to
the 3.0 I know. Um, with the new sizing,
we had to have everybody run through and
have them sized. So, Ellen Curtis will
come in with two representatives and
they have what are called sizing sets.
Our personnel then go through and they
try those sizing sets on and they mark
it down and that's recorded for us to
then go ahead and place our order. Uh
what we were finding is for instance my
sizing set um was based off of what we
had previously ordered and when I got it
it's vastly different. Um we're finding
that in in quite a few of the demo sets
that we got. So um we record those sets
and place the order. Now that we're
going back to the 3.0 we can essentially
just go back to the old order from three
years ago. Uh the email went out today
to all of our personnel. Hey, if you
have a sizing issue, if you've lost 25,
30 lbs, something like that, please come
in. We'll have you resized. Make sure
your gear properly fits you.
>> Okay. Any further comments or questions
for the committee for the chief?
Okay, we'll go to public comment in the
room. Any public comment in the room on
this item?
Seeing none, public comment online.
Any public comment online on this item?
Back to the committee. What's your
pleasure,
>> Mr. Chair? I move to approve an amount
not to exceed $331,491.
>> Been moved by Councilman White, second
by Councilman Moody.
>> Mr. Chair, I move to amend by substitute
quote dated September 18th, 2026.
>> Substitute moved by Council White,
second by Councilman Moody. Any further
comments or questions?
>> Oh, just a comment.
>> Councilman Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Chairman. you. Uh
just to confirm uh the does go down to
$316,758.64.
Is that correct?
>> Chair through you. I apologize. So
there's two quotes involved from 918 and
I should have explained that there are
86 sets that are in the red level trim
and then we have four new recruits
currently in our fire academy. So I had
to have another uh quote with four sets
in the yellow trim um that they'll have
to be provided also. So, they have two
full sets of um up-to-date gear. So,
there's two quotes there dated 918 that
should cover both trim levels and cover
all 90 sets. Okay.
>> Um
okay. All in favor signify by saying I.
Any opposed? None. Back on the main
motion. All in favor signify by saying
I.
Seeing that that is unanimous, uh the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to approve this purchase.
Next item
>> number 27E, consideration to purchase
between the city of Cheyenne and Axon
Enterprise Incorporated for the purchase
of incar cameras for the Cheyenne Police
Department for 10 recently ordered
police interceptors.
>> Staff report.
>> Mr. Chair, members of the committee, uh
good afternoon. Lieutenant Brady from
Cheyenne Police Department. Um, what you
have before you is a consideration of
purchase between the city of Cheyenne
and Axon Enterprise for the purchase of
INCAR camera systems uh for the Cheyenne
Police Department. This is going to be
going into 10 of our recently acquired
uh police interceptors that are set to
be delivered in February of 2027. This
is a sole source purchase. Therefore, uh
no other bids were requested. Um the
quote also includes a 39month
subscription for the 10 uh Axon fleet 3
incar cameras includes the cameras
operational software all the hardware
licensing agreements etc. Uh total
amount being requested is $88,41020
and I'm happy to stand by for any
further questions.
>> Any questions for the committee for the
department?
Nope. We'll go to public comment in the
room on this item.
Any public comment in the room? Public
comment online.
Any public comment online? Okay, back to
the committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chair, I move to approve an amount
not to exceed $88,41020.
>> It's been moved by Council White, second
by Councilman Wolf. Any further
discussion? All in favor signify by
saying I. Seeing that that votes
unanimous, the recommendation of the
finance committee, the next meeting of
the governing body will be to approve
the purchase. Next item, please.
>> Number 27F, consideration of bid number
E-127
for furnishing compost facility waste
hauling.
>> Staff report.
>> Good afternoon, chairman, committee
members. Craig Lavoy public works. This
contract will allow
our consultant or not our consultant but
our contractor to haul 18,500 cubic
yards of material to the landfill to be
used in recolation projects and
alternate or daily cover as well as
bring back 2,000 cubic yards of clean
soil to help us um process more top soil
blanded compost for our residents. And
the two bids received, Consolidated
Resources LLC was the low bidder at
$27,665.
And I recommend approval. I'll stand for
questions.
>> Any comments or questions on this bid
for Mr. B
Lavoy?
Nothing from the committee. We'll go to
public comment in the room.
Any public comment in the room? Any
public comment online?
No public comment online. Back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, I move to accept a bid
from Consolidated Resource LC amount not
to exceed $27,665.
>> Second.
>> It's been moved by Councilman Moody,
second by Councilman White. Any further
discussion?
All in favor signify by saying I.
Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to accept the bid. Next
item, please.
>> Number 27G, consideration of bid number
E-2-27
for furnishing one new instock special
operations SUV with a S or SSV platform
for Cheyenne Fire Rescue.
>> Staff report.
>> Good morning, council chair and members.
Uh Neil Danny, batten chief, Cheyenne
Fire Rescue. We [clears throat] have a
consideration for bid for you guys today
in the sum of $86,91847
for the purchase of an SUV for the
special operations division of Cheyenne
Fire Rescue.
Uh this vehicle be utilized for special
operations uh primarily for our tactical
EMS team and our community EMS.
>> Any comments or questions for the chief?
Councilman White.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair. through you,
Chief. Um,
what was the deliver? I see one of the
bids were were rejected uh because it
did not comply with the delivery time
frame. What was the delivery time frame?
>> So, uh through you, Mr. Chair, we had a
um
uh we were fairly confident we could uh
um allocate this vehicle locally that
was with an in stock unit and so we had
a pretty short time frame on it. Um we
we were actually asked initially I think
was uh the 30 days was our original time
delivery time frame and then we were
asked to extend it which we did for
another opportunity for another bidder.
Uh and I think he subsequently offered
up two additional time frames. Uh the
final f time frame wasund
150 days. So we went with the the
obviously the one that we could get a
hold of quickly.
Any further questions for the chief?
No. Any public comment in the room on
this item? Any public comment? Public
comment online.
No public comment online. Back to the
committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Mr. Chairman, um I move to accept the
bid from Phil Long Wong Ford of Denver
LLC in an amount not to exceed
$86,91847.
>> Second. Been moved by Councilman Wolf,
second by Councilman Moody. Any further
discussion? [snorts] All in favor
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> Seeing that that vote is unanimous, the
recommendation of the finance committee
at the next meeting of the governing
body will be to accept the bid. Next
item
>> number 27H. Consideration of bin number
E-3-27
for furnishing one new 2026 or newer cab
and chassis 4x4 with 12T forestry
chipper dump bed for the forestry divi
division
>> staff report.
>> Mr. Chair, Jason Sanchez, community
wreck and events. uh before even for
your consideration is a bid to replace
our old 2008 chipper truck and purchase
a new one from Fremont Ford Company in
the amount of $12,98.
Um if you approve this um bid, the truck
is scheduled to arrive in 180 days and I
will stand by for questions.
>> Questions from the committee for
director Sanchez on this item.
>> Question Council Moody.
>> Yep. Thank you, Mr. Chair. Thank you,
Mr. Sanchez. So on here coming previous
says bid rejected except this one says
multims did not meet specifications.
Just what were one or two of those
>> go ahead TJ
>> TJ Bartlewart purchasing manager chair
through to Councilman Moody. So in
reference to the bid from Altech
Industries that's the one you're
inquiring about correct. Uh so they they
we issued an addendum partway through
the bid process that changed multiple
bid specifications that we discussed
during the pre-bid meeting. They didn't
even use the addendum one specifications
to submit their bid. So they missed an
addendum in whole. They didn't have a
bid guarantee. Um and they said no to
just multiple line items that were
addressed at the pre- bid meeting. So
they just had a pretty significant
oversight in the bid submission process.
So that's a pretty high level view for
you. Thank you, [snorts]
>> Councilman Wolf.
>> Uh, Mr. Chairman, thank you. Through
you. Um, Director Sanchez, this this is
just the truck but not the chipper
machine. Is that right,
>> Mr. Chair? Through you. Uh, correct.
>> U, and um, do you replace the Mr.
Chairman, I'm sorry. Through through
you, do you replace does the chipper get
replaced obviously on a on a completely
different schedule? And
sorry, correct, Mr. chair through you.
That is correct. I was just looking at
TJ to see if we had a date in mind, but
uh it it will be to replace at a
different time.
>> Okay, we'll go to public comment in the
room on this item. Any public comment in
the room? Any public comment online on
this item?
Public comment online seeing none. Back
to the committee. What's your pleasure?
>> Uh Mr. Chairman, I move to accept the
bid from Fremont Motor Company in amount
not to exceed $12,980.
>> Been moved by Councilman Moody, seconded
by Councilman Wolf. Any further
discussion? All in favor signify by
saying I.
>> Seeing that there's none opposed, that
vote is unanimous. Recommendation in the
finance committee at the next meeting of
the governing body will be to accept the
bid. With that, that's our last item. We
are adjourned.
Hey, Miss Johnson, I have a question for
you.